<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: languages | antonym.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://antonym.org//blog/categories/languages/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://antonym.org//"/>
  <updated>2014-02-26T09:06:01+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://antonym.org//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gavin Baker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is Rust?]]></title>
    <link href="http://antonym.org//2013/10/what-is-rust.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T20:50:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://antonym.org//2013/10/what-is-rust</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/">Rust</a> is a compiled, hybrid imperative/object-
oriented/functional language. It appeals directly to any C++ developer who has
battled with memory management, and Python developers who long for faster code.
So why might you be interested in learning Rust?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>It&rsquo;s <strong>compiled</strong>, so it&rsquo;s fast. Rust uses <a href="http://www.llvm.org/">LLVM</a> as the
compilation engine, and benefits from all its optimisation and native code
generation support that targets ARM and Intel processors.</p>

<p>Rust uses <strong>type inference</strong>, so you can write cleaner, simpler code while
retaining the benefits of strong static typing. It also supports <strong>generic</strong> and
<strong>algebraic types</strong>, which offers a far richer type system than C++.</p>

<p>There are no <code>NULL</code> pointers, thus rendering an entire class of bugs impossible.
This alone is worth a serious look, as the security and reliability implications
are huge.</p>

<p>Rust is a brace-oriented like C/C++, so many aspects of the syntax will be
immediately familiar to existing developers.</p>

<p>Memory ownership semantics are rich, strict and enforced. There are owned
pointers, shared pointers and <em>optional</em> garbage-collection.</p>

<p>Rust has first-class <strong>concurrency</strong> support, featuring lightweight tasks
and message passing.</p>

<p>What does it look like? I would describe it as terse &ndash; or rather, minimalist.</p>

<p>``` rust
fn main() {</p>

<pre><code>println!("Hello, world");
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Ok, that&rsquo;s not very useful. How about a naïve Fibonacci function:</p>

<p>``` rust
fn fib(n: uint) &ndash;> uint {</p>

<pre><code>match n {
    0..1    =&gt; 1,
    _       =&gt; fib(n-1) + fib(n-2)
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Yes, Rust has <strong>pattern matching</strong> just like Haskell. Forget about the simple
<code>switch</code> statement &ndash; <code>match</code> is super-powerful and flexible, supporting ranges,
options and destructuring fields from <code>struct</code>s.</p>

<p>What about some tasks:</p>

<p>``` rust
fn test_tasks() {</p>

<pre><code>println("About to spawn...");

do spawn {
    println("Hello from the first subtask!");
}

do spawn {
    println("Hello from another subtask!");
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Despite having spent years working in C++, I have often lamented its
shortcomings. Yet until recently, no other language seems to have come close to
competing with C++ as a systems language.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://dlang.org">D programming language</a> looks very interesting, and aims
to provide a worthy alternative to C++.  However, last time I looked, there was
a schism over the runtime libraries which made adoption difficult. Uncertainty
about such a fundamental aspect is not reassuring for potential users.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.go-lang.org/">Go programming language</a> from Google is fantastic,
and I have already used it on a number of small projects. The only shortcoming I
see here is the garbage collection, which makes real-time systems impractical.</p>

<p>Rust has great promise, and also has both Mozilla and Samsung backing its
progress. There is a vibrant, friendly and smart community behind it, and a
growing number of third-party libraries are supported. I am very optimistic
about the future of Rust, and look forward to contributing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
